<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two most srange [sic] and notable examples, shewed at Lyshborne the 26. day of Ianuarie now last past The one by striking dumme two of the cheefe of the holy-house, as they were pronouncing the sentence of death against two English Mariners, vnto whom they had offered great promotion, to haue them to serue against the King of France, and their owne countrie. The other within sixe dayes then next following, by burning two ships of corne in the harboure there, which was brought out of France to releeue the King his enimies: an example most wonderfull. ... Affirmed for truth by those men vnder named, of honest reputation, being present at the dooing thereof, the one maister of the ship called the Fortune: the other maister of the Flying Harte. Hance Hogenberge, &amp; Adrian van How. Signed for truthe in the presence of those here vnderwritten. Henry Roberts. Water Mantle. Iohn Nshe. Robert Ihones.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 19 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05586</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15704</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119667</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854874</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854874</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20329</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05586)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20329)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 475:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two most srange [sic] and notable examples, shewed at Lyshborne the 26. day of Ianuarie now last past The one by striking dumme two of the cheefe of the holy-house, as they were pronouncing the sentence of death against two English Mariners, vnto whom they had offered great promotion, to haue them to serue against the King of France, and their owne countrie. The other within sixe dayes then next following, by burning two ships of corne in the harboure there, which was brought out of France to releeue the King his enimies: an example most wonderfull. ... Affirmed for truth by those men vnder named, of honest reputation, being present at the dooing thereof, the one maister of the ship called the Fortune: the other maister of the Flying Harte. Hance Hogenberge, &amp; Adrian van How. Signed for truthe in the presence of those here vnderwritten. Henry Roberts. Water Mantle. Iohn Nshe. Robert Ihones.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by A. Jeffes] for William Barley, and are to be solde at his shop in Newgate Market,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1591.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ (-A1, B4).</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A worthy example of burning two ships of corne.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Elizabeth, 1558-1603 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lisburn (Northern Ireland) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:20329:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 113 -->
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20329:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 113 -->
            <p>TWO MOST SRANGE AND notable examples, shewed at Lyshborne the 26. day of Ianuarie now laſt paſt.</p>
            <p>THE ONE BY STRIKING DVMME two of the cheefe of the Holy-houſe, as they were <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing the ſentence of death againſt two Engliſh Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners, vnto whom they had offered great promotions, to haue them to ſerue againſt the King of France, and their owne Countrie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other within ſixe dayes then next following, by <hi>burning two Ships of Corne in the Harboure there, which was brought out of</hi> France <hi>to releeue the King his enimies: An example moſt wonderfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A notable warning to ſuch Engliſh Marchants, which <hi>for their owne benefit, by carrying our victuals away, impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueriſh our Countrey, and ſtrengthen the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of God and our Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Affirmed for truth by thoſe men vnder named, of <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest reputation, being preſent at the dooing thereof, the one Maiſter of the Ship called the</hi> Fortune: <hi>the other Maister of the</hi> Flying Harte.</p>
            <p>Hance Hogenberge, <hi>&amp;</hi> Adrian van How.</p>
            <p>Signed for truthe in the preſence of thoſe here vnderwritten.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Henry Roberts.</item>
               <item>Iohn Naſhe.</item>
               <item>Water Mantle.</item>
               <item>Robert Ihones.</item>
            </list>
            <p>LONDON Printed for William Barley, and are to be ſolde <hi>at his ſhop in Newgate Market.</hi> ANNO. 1591.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:20329:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 114 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:20329:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 114 -->
            <head>A worthie example of burning two Ships of Corne brought for the releefe of the enemie vnto <hi>Liſhborne.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Moneth of <hi>Auguſt, 1586.</hi> There was taken by the <hi>Spaniards</hi> a tall Ship called the <hi>Barke rowe,</hi> now belonging vnto the Towne of Newcaſtell vpon Tine, the Maiſter of which Ship at that time was one <hi>Iohn Harriſon,</hi> borne in Cornwall, and foure others with him, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were found to be men of reputation, and of good experience in their Arte, were had in more regarde then the reſt. And whereas the company were all condemned to the Galleyes, where ſome of them yet ſerue. They were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto the cuſtody of a Caualier, who had charge to vſe them with great curteſie. One whole yeare remained they in the keeping of this their firſt Hoaſte, with very great en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment, where they were often viſited with Friers and other religious perſons, which very earneſtly laboured to drawe them both from God, and their allegiance to their Prince, which howe earneſt ſo euer they were ſolicited, it pleaſed God to ſtrengthen them, ſo that their hearts were hardened againſt their religion and them, who ſcorned to how to any Idols, knowing that they bee but ſtones, and the
<pb facs="tcp:20329:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 115 -->workes of mens hands, and therefore vtterly refuſed to giue the glorie of the Omnipotent God, to ſuch traſh as they ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured. Theſe ſhauelings, when as they ſawe no hope to winne thoſe ſoules as they terme it, conferring together tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching their obſtinacie, thought to prooue if ſome haſher v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage might make them yeelde: wherefore the Cardinall of <hi>Liſhborne,</hi> Viceroye to the King of <hi>Spayne,</hi> at whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund they were: being enformed by ſuch as he ſent, howe they aunſwered to ſuch demaundes which were required of them, commaunded that the ſayde <hi>Iohn Harriſon,</hi> and his foure companions, ſhould all bee ommitted vnto the Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition or Holy houſe, and there to abide ſuch puniſhment as theyr manner is to laye vpon the Children of GOD, which was preſently doone as he gaue in charge, and they all ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerally impriſoned, in ſuch loathſome places as it would haue pittied a man to haue ſeene theyr eſtate, during the time of their durance there.</p>
            <p>Twiſe euerye weeke would they ſende vnto them, villaines diſguiſed in the counterfaite attire of a Deuill, which cruelly, like him that he repreſented, would ſcourge them with whips of Wyer, ſo that theyr fleſhe was moſt greeuouſlye torne with thoſe tormentors, liuing with no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vyandes, but onely with boiled Barlye, and faire water. of which they ſcantly had theyr bellyes full. Thus by Gods fauour, who ſtrengthneth his ſeruants, continued thoſe our Countreymen ſtedfaſt in the faith of Chriſt, refuſing all the vanities of the worlde, to beare the Croſſe of their Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer (Chriſt Ieſus.)</p>
            <p>Two yeares ſpente they in theſe extremities, in which time two of them by Gods viſitation dyed, whom theſe <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niballes</hi> would not allowe Chriſtian buriall vnto, for that they dyed not in their faith.</p>
            <p>Well, their great Fleete beeing prepared for England, men of ſkyll for the Coaſt was greatlye wantnig, ſo that there was great meanes made for all men of what nation ſo
<pb facs="tcp:20329:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 115 -->euer that would take charge, Amongſt which there was ſent for, this <hi>Iohn Harriſon,</hi> and his two conſorts <hi>Peter Bryan</hi> his Mate, a verye good Marriner, and <hi>William Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thewes,</hi> the Gunner, braue men, and of ſtoute Courage.</p>
            <p>Thoſe men being brought vnto the preſence of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall, humbling themſelues as to the Kinges Viceroye one their knee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Cardinall came to take them vp, and bleſſed them with his hand, making on their heads the ſigne of the Holy Croſſe, ſpeaking two or three wordes in Lattin, which they vnderſtood not, this <hi>William Mathewes,</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how he vſed the other two, when as he offered to bleſſe him, thruſt away his hands, and tolde him, that his bleſſing was rather a curſſe, (to them that beleeued it was of anye force) then a bleſſing: Which wordes vnderſtoode by an Engliſh Frier, appointed to be theyr interpreter, and reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto others ſtanding by.</p>
            <p>The ſayde <hi>Mathewes</hi> was greeuouſly buffeted, in the Cardinals preſence, whereat he ſeemed to be very diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. Well after ſome outragious wordes offered to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thewes</hi> for refuſing this Holy Fathers bleſſing. The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall began againe to worke ſuch meanes and perſwaſions as he heſt could, to drawe them vnto his will, proteſting that hee was ſuch a fauourer of their cauſes, that hee was gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to ſee or heere of their miſerye: yet (quoth hee) I haue intreated thoſe Holy Fathers. Seniors of the Church of Rome, cheefeſt in commiſſion for his Holineſſe, to mitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate the extremitie of the lawes, for the puniſhment of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes prouided, ſo that yee will bee reformed, and become Catholikes, and liue like Chriſtians, forſaking your damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble opinions, which vnleſſe you doo, you cannot be ſaued. (It may be) quoth this Holy Cardinall, that your deſire to liue in your Countrie with your freends, maye cauſe you ſtande vpon more pointes then willinglye you would. If that be the cauſe ſtande not one ſuch tearmes, for on mine honour you ſhall haue ſufficient maintenance out of the Kings
<pb facs="tcp:20329:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 116 -->treaſurye. Be ruled, and you ſhall liue in ſo good <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with vs, as the beſt men in England. You haue heard how the Catholike Princes, haue ioyned their forces to <unclear>abate</unclear> the pride of your Countrie, and to make them know the liuing God, for which entended voyage our prouiſion is all ready, and knowing by reportes of ſuch Matriners whome in ſecret I haue ſente to conferre with you, that you are men of ſufficiencie, to take the charge of good <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hippes, for that you are borne in that damned Countrey, I haue thought good to make you offers of fauoure ſuch as your owne Countrie ſhall neuer afforde mell<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> ſimple birthe.</p>
            <p>Firſt from your impriſonment you ſhall be <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, next ſhall you be conducted to all places where our forces are, where euery of you ſhall make choiſe of what <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſe, Pinnis, or other, you will ſerue in as Maiſter: where <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> dooing your true entents, like faithfull Souldiers of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God, and his Catholike Churche of Rome. And God ſhall giue thoſe miſcreants into your handes, whereof there is no doubt, you ſhall be there aduanſed to what honours you will require, and <hi>500.</hi> Duckets monthly to be paide you of the King, if you thinke well of this my offer, let me ſee your willingneſſe to confirme my requeſt.</p>
            <p>Thoſe faithfull ſeruants of God, whoſe comfort is the great God of Iſraell, hauing hearkened vnto the alluring ſpeeches of the Cardinall, as meanes to pull them from the trueth calling to minde howe Chriſt himſelfe was <unclear>tempted</unclear> of the Deuill by worldly promotions, <hi>Iob</hi> tryed and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, yet remayned conſtant in Chriſt Ieſus, took<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> on that God which comforteth the diſtreſſed, who feeling the fleſhe weake and willing, hardeneth theyr heartes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their offers, and the Popiſhe Doctrine preached vnto them. And <hi>Mathewes</hi> in the name of the reſt <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> aunſwered.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20329:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 116 -->
Your grace hath ſaid ſufficient in mine opinion, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> your <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>eſt Catholick from his allegiance, both from Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt whom you ſerue, and the Kings ſeruice: yet ſhall your grace know, we are Engliſhmen, who not obſtinatly refuſe your gracious offers, but in that they are offered to the ende <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhoulde fall from GOD, forſaking the true doctrine of Chriſt, to cleaue to your damnable opinions: from good ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>, you woulde drawe vs like Rebels, to beare Armes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Countrey where we receiued life, ſeeking to ſhed the blood of Chriſtians, (a damnable raſe) bereauing our own bloodes with the Enemies ſword, by whom we were nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, thereby to heape the vengeance of God vpon vs. No, no, my Lord, (quoth he) rather then it ſhall be ſaide that an Engliſh man ſhall deliuer his Countrey into the hands of the deuill, (for no better I account you, nor none of your Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whoſe mindes be butcherlike, delighting in nothing but <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>) let me die, and my bretheren with me, or inflickt ſuch puniſhments on vs as you pleaſe, that God, which deliuered <hi>Deuell</hi> from the Lyons, the three innocent children from the burning Ouen, and many other wonders hath ſhewed for his <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhall deliuer vs from your tiraunie, or giue vs the like patience to endure it.</p>
            <p>The Cardinall hearing his offers ſo reiected, was gréeued not a little, wherefore he commaunded them away to pryſon, whether going, they were by ſuch as heard theyr aunſweres, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and abuſed, as it might gréeue a man to think on it. Thys purpoſe fayling, the Cardinall tooke order that they were ſent vnto the Duke of <hi>Sauoy,</hi> to ſerue in hys Gallyes, where two of them remained euer ſince, vntill Chriſtmas <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> there came from <hi>Sauoy</hi> a power of men, with Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition and victuals, to goe for Brittaine as it is ſuppoſed, in which Fleete came thoſe two which were left liuing, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, <hi>Iohn Hariſon</hi> and <hi>William Matthewes,</hi> who on the xxiiij. day of Ianuary, (after theyr computation) were ſent for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine before the Inquiſition, and in like manner as before with great fauours offered libertie, if now they would ſerue,
<pb facs="tcp:20329:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 117 -->and larger offers then before.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Matthewes</hi> in the name of the other and for himſelfe, aunſwered, that neceſſitie could not draw him from the ioyes of heauen, to liue in pleaſure on the earth, and therefore per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded them, that they ſhoulde no more vrge him vnto it; for it was friuolous, and rather then he would hold vp his hand, or giue the leaſt worde of aduiſe to preiudice his Prince and Countrey, he would willingly yeeld to what torment ſoeuer.</p>
            <p>The States of Holly-houſe demaunded of <hi>Hariſon,</hi> if his minde were ſo reſolute as that damned. Here<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ique his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion? Who aunſwered, in no damnable opinions he wold be ruled by him, but if hee remained in thoſe opinions which he did profeſſe, he would confirme with his blood what <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thewes</hi> had ſpoken. When they ſawe that no perſwaſions might auaile them, nor miſery which gréeuouſly they had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured, mooue them to forſake theyr true God, they were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againe to pryſon, and the Prelates called a counſell what to doo with them, who hauing debated thereon ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, determined to burne them to the enſample of others.</p>
            <p>The next day they were againe called before them, when after ſome ſpéeches vſed in like manner: to winne them from theyr opinion, and that it woulde not preuaile, with rayling ſpéech they recounted vnto them, how fauourably it had plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Cardinall to deale with them, and to ſpare their liues, willing that they ſhoulde liue: but ſince nothing might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, they were now eyther to receiue theyr former <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, or to prepare themſelues to die.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſpéeches could not terrifie them, but as men deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous for Chriſt and his truth, to bee freed from the torment which they endured, craued no fauour, but wiſhed them to proceede.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>The Iudge giuing ſentence of death againſt them.</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Theyr aunſwere giuen, <hi>Don Fredericke</hi> chiefeſt in the Comiſſion ſtoode vppe, and as he was pronouncing the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of death againſt thoſe innocents, a ſuddaine feare fell vpon them all that were preſent, and <hi>Don Fredericke</hi> was ſtriken dumbe, that hys tongue foltering in his mouth, hee could not ſpeake a word. Thys ſtrooke a terror in them all.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20329:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 118 -->
               <hi>Don Frederick</hi> béeing carried away, <hi>Don Franciſco</hi> chiefe Ambnere to the Cardinall ſtoode vp, &amp; rayling againſt thoſe pooremen, told them, that they wrought by ſorcery &amp; witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft, calling them deuils, and vſing other bad ſpéeches, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting God was of power, to ſhowe his might in puniſhing thoſe miſcreants, vpon whom it pleaſed him to ſhew the like example, by taking from him, not onely the vſe of his tongue, wherewith he abuſed thoſe ſeruants of GOD, but alſo his lymbes, to the great admiration of the company, ſo that hee was carried away likewiſe from the iudgement place.</p>
            <p>Then fell the people generally to rayling on them, and with gréeuous ſtrokes to lay vpon them, ſo that if GOD had not mooued one of the State to pittie them, they had béen pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſlaine amongſt them. From thence they were againe committed to pryſon, where they endured all the extremities poſſible for men to abide, whom God for his mercies ſake ſtrengthen, and releaſe at his pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Within two dayes following, another example worth the noting happened. There were ryding in the Harbour cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Hulkes, to the number of <hi>26.</hi> ſayles, ſome of <hi>Lubicke,</hi> ſome other of <hi>Auſterdame,</hi> and of other places of the Eaſt Countries, into which harbour alſo came two ſmall Barkes of S. <hi>Mallowes</hi> in Fraunce, loden with Corne for prouiſion of the Kings Fleete, which is expected to come for Brittaine. Thoſe two French ſhips, hauing mored themſelues a ſtarne a Hulke of <hi>Auſterdame</hi> called the <hi>Fortune,</hi> chaunced to haue her Anckors come home, and thwarted the French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſo, that it put him in ſome daunger, that betwixt them grew ſome hote ſpeeches. The next day the Frenchman are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted the Hulke for his damage, and accuſed vnto the Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſixe of thoſe Hulkes, that theyr traffique was for Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhmen, and that the goods were all Engliſhmens, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon they were ſtayed to the Kings vſe, and theyr men im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, which the Duchmen denied, as iuſtly they might. But the Frenchman on his oath auerred the ſame, ſo that there was no remedie but to looſe theyr goods and endanger
<pb facs="tcp:20329:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 118 -->themſelues. Yet God who ſéeth the ſecrets of all mens harts, and canat hys pleaſure lay them open to the world, to ſhewe hys wonders on earth &amp; make his name more feared, ſhewed thys moſt gracious and wonderfull miracle, within <hi>6.</hi> dayes after the conuiction of thoſe Flemmings.</p>
            <p>The Frenchman hauing taken order for vnloding of their Corn<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, as the Maiſter of the Barke which accuſed them, was buſted with his companions, a ſuddain Lightning with grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous weather happened, in which ſtorme, a Thunderſtone <unclear>as</unclear> it is ſuppoſed, ſlew the Maiſter, who had before ferſworne himſelfe, daſhing his braynes about the ſhyp, and fired both the Shyps of Corne, which could not be quenched by all the meanes they coulde make, nor ſaue one penniworth of the ſame, to the great wonder of all the beholders.</p>
            <p>After which example, the Flemings ſuing by their friends for theyr libertie, cauſed certaine of the companie on theyr oathes to be examined, touching the accuſation giuen by the Maiſter of the Barke againſt them, who affirmed before the Cardinall, that the Maiſter had confeſt amongſt them diuers times, that he did it but for reuenge, and would often reioyce in the miſery of the men, who by his meanes were in danger both of goods and life. Vpon whoſe reports they were all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, and theyr goods deliuered, but not without great charge and hinderaunce.</p>
            <p>Thus gentle Reader, haue you heard the works of God, in reuenging hys ſeruants on thoſe of authoritie, who oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them, which lye ſtill in moſt pittifull manner, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie, albeit they haue not wanted for the counſels of the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proouedſt Phiſitions in the whole Land. But God, is iuſt, and will be knowne, I pray God thys example prooue of ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent force, to turne their deuiliſh mindes to the knowledge of the true God, who defendeth hys children, and will puniſh thoſe ſtifnecked miſcreants that diſhonour his name.</p>
            <p>In thys Pamphlet alſo mayſt thou ſée the reward of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie, and the iuſt iudgement of God, in bereauing hys lyfe,
<pb facs="tcp:20329:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 119 -->that ſought the liues and deſtruction of thoſe hee had neuer ſéene, for a ſmall offence by caſualtie committed, for which they offered him large amendes which might not ſuffiſe, as alſo if Gods iudgements might be coniectured by men, howe God was angry, in releeuing thoſe which ſéeke to diſhonour his Name, with that Corne which would haue doone good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt that famous King of Fraunce his Campe where it is needed, yet purloyned by thoſe Rebels of his own Countrey, to maintaine his enemies. God make euery man to amende his owne faultes, and to feare, that God will inflict the lyke plague vpon our Countrimen, that for gaine rob the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth of victuals, and maintaine the Enemies of God and our Country. God giue euery man grace to forbeare ſo deſirous a minde of couetouſnes, and make vs thankfull for all his benefits, which thorow his mercies we daily receiue. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20329:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 119 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
